<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Machine Learning on Hi, I&#39;m Eklavya Chopra</title>
    <link>/series/machine-learning/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Machine Learning on Hi, I&#39;m Eklavya Chopra</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Jun 2020 17:15:12 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/series/machine-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Linear Regression</title>
      <link>/posts/2020/06/linear-regression/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jun 2020 17:15:12 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2020/06/linear-regression/</guid>
      <description>This post will cover the linear regression implementation (From Scratch using Pytorch).
Linear Regression Equation : Overview Linear regression attempts to fit a line of best fit to a data set, using one or more features as coefficients for a linear equation. It is an approach for modelling the relationship between dependent variable and independent variables.
In a linear regression model, each target (dependent) variable is estimated to be a weighted sum of the input variables, offset by some constant, known as a bias :</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Object Detection using SIFT</title>
      <link>/posts/2019/03/object-detection-using-sift/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Mar 2019 17:15:12 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2019/03/object-detection-using-sift/</guid>
      <description>Object Detection using SIFT algorithm SIFT (Scale Invariant Feature Transform) is a feature detection algorithm in computer vision to detect and describe local features in images. It was created by David Lowe from the University British Columbia in 1999. David Lowe presents the SIFT algorithm in his original paper titled Distinctive Image Features from Scale-Invariant Keypoints.
Image features extracted by SIFT are reasonably invariant to various changes such as their llumination image noise, rotation, scaling, and small changes in viewpoint.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>