<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>machine learning on Hi, I&#39;m Eklavya Chopra</title>
    <link>/tags/machine-learning/</link>
    <description>Recent content in machine learning on Hi, I&#39;m Eklavya Chopra</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 Mar 2019 17:15:12 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/machine-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Face Detection using Histogram of Oriented Gradients</title>
      <link>/posts/2019/03/face-detection-using-histogram-of-oriented-gradients/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Mar 2019 17:15:12 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2019/03/face-detection-using-histogram-of-oriented-gradients/</guid>
      <description>What is Histogram of Oriented Gradients (HOG)? Navneet Dalal and Bill Triggs introduced Histogram of Oriented Gradients(HOG) features in 2005. Histogram of Oriented Gradients (HOG) is a feature descriptor used in image processing, mainly for object detection. A feature descriptor is a representation of an image or an image patch that simplifies the image by extracting useful information from it.
The principle behind the histogram of oriented gradients descriptor is that local object appearance and shape within an image can be described by the distribution of intensity gradients or edge directions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hopfield Network</title>
      <link>/posts/2019/01/hopfield-network/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2019/01/hopfield-network/</guid>
      <description>Hopfield Network is a recurrent neural network with bipolar threshold neurons. In this article, we will go through in depth along with an implementation. Before going into Hopfield network, we will revise basic ideas like Neural network and perceptron.
A neural network is a mathematical model or computational model inspired by biological neural networks. It consists of an interconnected group of artiﬁcial neurons. The sructure and functioning of the central nervous system constituing neurons, axons, dentrites and syanpses which make up the processing parts of the biological neural networks were the original inspiration that led to the developement of computational models of neural networks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Object Detection Techniques</title>
      <link>/posts/2018/04/object-detection-techniques/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2018/04/object-detection-techniques/</guid>
      <description>In this article, we will understand what is object detection, why we need to do object detection and the basic idea behind various techniques used to solved this problem. We start with the basic techniques like Viola Jones face detector to some of the advanced techniques like Single Shot Detector. Some the the techniques are:
 Viola Jones face detector Object Detection using Histogram of Oriented Gradients (HOG) Features Scale-invariant feature transform (SIFT) AlexNet Region-based Convolutional Network (R-CNN) You Only Look Once (YOLO) Single Shot Detector (SSD)  What is Object Detection?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>